So let's get started with re-act what why and how.
imdi neden ve nasl tekrar hareket etmeye balayalm.
Let's start with the what is re-act question.
Yeniden hareket sorusu ile balayalm.
And let me cite a phrase from the official reac page reactor's of javascript library for Boulding user
Boulding kullanc arayzleri iin resmi reac sayfas reaktrnn javascript kitaplndan bir cmle atf yapmama
interfaces.
izin verin.
Now that's a nice sentence but what does it mean.
imdi bu gzel bir cmle ama ne demektir.
The first important part is the javascript library part.
lk nemli nokta, javascript kitapl blmdr.
It is a javascript library.
Bu bir javascript kitapldr.
It is about building javascript driven apps re-act apps run in the browser that don't run on the server.
Taraycda altrlan, sunucu zerinde almayan javascript ynlendirmeli uygulamalar yeniden aktarma uygulamalaryla ilgilidir.
They run in the browser and that gives us a great advantage.
Taraycda alrlar ve bize byk bir avantaj salar.
Things happen instantly since they happen to user's browser.
Kullanclarn taraycsna ne olduklarndan annda olurlar.
We don't have to wait for a server response to get a new page or to render something new.
Yeni bir sayfa almak veya yeni bir ey oluturmak iin bir sunucu yant beklemek zorunda deiliz.
Do you have an important part in that sentence.
Cmlede nemli bir yere sahipsiniz mi?
Is the user interface as part user interfaces are basically what the user sees and reacts is all about
Kullanc arabirimi, ksmen kullanc arayzleri olarak temelde kullancnn grd ve tepki verdii ey,
using components for building these.
bunlar oluturmak iin bileenleri kullanmaktr.
If you think about it you can split up any web page into components.
Dnrseniz, herhangi bir web sayfasn bileenlere ayrabilirsiniz.
Here's an example.
te bir rnek.
This was just any random web page we can think of we might have this header area a side bar and then
Bu, herhangi bir rasgele web sayfasyd, bu stbilgi alanna yan ubuk ve sada baz
on the right some content.
ierik olabilir diye dnebiliriz.
Now we clearly can split this up into components.
imdi bunu aka bileenlere ayrabiliriz.
We would have a head or a component a sidebar component and then a headline in the article content component.
Makale ierii bileeninde bir balk veya bir bileene bir kenar ubuu bileeni, ardndan bir balk olurduk.
Now why is thinking like it is important or useful.
imdi neden nemli ya da yararl olduu dnlyor.
Because if we split up our web app or web site into such components we can build these building blocks
nk eer web uygulamanz veya web sitemizi byle bileenlere ayrabilirsek, bu
these components as contained pieces of code.
yap talarn bu bileenleri ierdii gibi oluturabiliriz.
We don't have to build our entire web page as one bigger picture.
Tm web sayfamz daha byk bir resim olarak oluturmak zorunda deiliz.
We can build all these tiny things on their own.
Btn bu kk eyleri kendi balarna yapabiliriz.
This of course makes working in teams easier.
Bu tabii ki takm almasn daha kolaylatryor.
But even if we're working alone it makes it easy for us to keep our code manageable if we change the
Yalnz alsak bile bal daha sonra deitirirsek kodumuzun ynetilebilir
headline later on.
olmasn kolaylatrr.
We only have to go into debt component and update it and we don't have to find that code on our entire
Sadece bor unsuruna girip gncelliyoruz ve bu kodu tm web sayfas
web page code.
kodumuzda bulmamz gerekmiyor.
We all can easily reuse components then if we have a list item component and we want to output a list
bileenimiz varsa ve bu iyi liste elerinin bir listesini kartmak istiyoruz, o zaman yalnzca kodu
of these well list items then we only have to write the code once and can then easily reuse it because
bir kez yazmak zorunda kaldk ve sonra nemli olduu iin kolayca yeniden kullanabilirsek, tm bileenleri kolayca yeniden kullanabiliriz.
that's important.
Bir liste esi
Riette components can be thought of as custom HVM elements in the end you're just writing custom HVM
Riette bileenleri zel HVM eleri olarak dnlebilir, bu nedenle yalnzca zel HVM posta eleri
mail elements does not react about and it therefore solves the problem of having to build complex user
yazarsnz ve tepki vermezler; bu nedenle, HLL ve Javascript'in size bakm yapabilen ynetilebilir yazarak
interfaces with what HLL and Javascript gives you by writing maintainable manageable and reusable pieces
verdii karmak kullanc arabirimlerini oluturma sorununu zer ve kullanmanz gereken yere nerede olursanz olun
of that code which you can throw into your web app wherever you need to use it.
web uygulamanza atabileceiniz bu kodun tekrar kullanlabilir paralar.
Let's have a look at some examples.
Baz rneklere bir gz atalm.